A Finding Aid to the Wallace Berman Papers, 1907-1979 (bulk 1955-1979), in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Wallace Berman papers
1907-1979
bulk 1955-1979
Archives of American Art
Berman, Wallace, 1926-1976
AAA.bermwall
Archival Resource Key
5 Linear feet
The Wallace Berman papers date from 1907 to 1979 (bulk 1955-1979). The collection measures 5 linear feet and presents a cursory overview of Berman's career as an assemblage artist and poet. The collection contains business correspondence, letters from other artists and writers of the Beat movement, writings by others, scattered artwork by Berman, photographs by Robert F. Heinecken, and sound recordings of poetry readings.
Biographical Note
Wallace Berman was born in 1926 in Staten Island, New York. In the 1930s, his family moved to the Jewish district in Los Angeles. After being expelled from high school for gambling in the early 1940s, Berman immersed himself in the growing West Coast jazz scene. During this period, he briefly attended the Jepson Art School and Chouinard Art School, but departed when he found the training too academic for his needs.
In 1949, while working in a factory finishing antique furniture, he began to make sculptures from unused scraps and reject materials. By the early 1950s, Berman had become a full-time artist and an active figure in the beat community in Los Angeles and San Francisco. Many art historians consider him to be the "father" of the California assemblage movement. Moving between the two cities, Berman devoted himself to his mail art publication Semina, which contained a sampling of beat poetry and images selected by Berman.
In 1963, permanently settled in Topanga Canyon in the Los Angeles area, Berman began work on verifax collages (printed images, often from magazines and newspapers, mounted in collage fashion onto a flat surface, sometimes with solid bright areas of acrylic paint). He continued creating these works, as well as rock assemblages, until his death in 1976.
Scope and Content Note
The Wallace Berman papers, 1907-1979 (bulk 1955-1979), measure 5 linear feet and present a cursory overview of Berman's career as an assemblage artist and poet. The collection is valuable not only for its documentation of the work of Wallace Berman, but for its documentation of the California beat movement of the late 1950s through the early 1970s.
Found are numerous letters, writings, poems, and other published material which portray the thoughts, attitudes, and trends popular in a prominent underground culture which eventually led to radical changes in America and American art. The collection contains business correspondence, letters from other artists and writers of the beat movement, writings by others, scattered artwork by Berman, and photographs by Robert F. Heinecken. In addition, the collection contains files for Berman's mail art publications Semina and S.M.S. Also of note is the large volume of printed material (2.7 feet), much of it in the form of books and other published material. Sound recordings include poets Michael McClure, Kenneth Patchen, David Melzer, and another unidentified writer performing their work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into nine series which generally reflect material type.
With the exception of the letters in Series 1, each series is arranged chronologically. The original arrangement of the letters has been maintained, with a chronological arrangement of miscellaneous business letters and an alphabetical arrangement of the letters from Berman's more prominent colleagues.
Missing Title
Series 1: Letters, 1957-1979, undated (box 1, 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Notes from Interview, 1967 (box 1, 1 folder)
Series 3: Writings by Others, 1972, undated (box 1, 6 folders)
Series 4: Artwork, 1956-1976 (box 1, 4 folders)
Series 5: Semina, 1955-1967 (boxes 1-2, 26 folders)
Series 6: S. M. S., 1968 (box 2, 1 folders)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1907-1976 (boxes 2-5, 2.7 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1956-1976 (box 5, 6 folders)
Series 9: Sound Recordings, 1962-1965 (box 5, 6 folders)
Provenance
The Wallace Berman papers were donated by Tosh Berman, Wallace Berman's son, in 1992.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy. Use of audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Alternative Forms Available
This collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 5282-5284 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Most of the sound recordings have been digitized for research access and are available at the Archives of American Art offices.
Works of art; Drawings; Poets; Sound recordings; Collage; Art -- California -- San Francisco Bay Area; Assemblage (Art); Assemblage artists; Photographs; Beat generation; Photography, Artistic; Heinecken, Robert, 1931-; Hirschman, Jack, 1933-; DeFeo, Jay, 1929-1989; Herms, George, 1935-; Jess, 1923-; Hopper, Dennis, 1936-; Jordan, Patricia M., 1937-1989; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Bengston, Billy Al; Di Prima, Diane; Fonda, Peter, 1940-; Duncan, Robert Edward, 1919-; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Wieners, John, 1934-; McClure, Michael; Lamantia, Philip, 1927-; Miller, Henry, 1891-; Meltzer, David; Perkoff, Stuart Z.; Patchen, Kenneth, 1911-1972; Sherman, Donald; Ruscha, Edward
- Letters, 1957-1979, undated; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet box 1, OV 7
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of miscellaneous business letters, ten letters from Berman, and letters from colleagues.
  Arrangement note
  The letters are arranged chronologically.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Letters are on reel 5282.
  - Miscellaneous Business Letters, 1959-1975, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - From Wallace Berman, 1960-1964, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - From Branaman, Robert, undated; Archival Resource Key; (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - From Collins, Jess and R. D., 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key; (4 letters) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - From DeFeo, Jay, 1965-1973; Archival Resource Key; (5 letters) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - From DiPrima, Diane, 1979; Archival Resource Key; (1 letter enclosing a braid of hair) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - From Driscoll, Bob, 1964; Archival Resource Key; (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [From Duncan, Robert], 1963; Archival Resource Key; (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - From Ginsberg, Allen, 1965; Archival Resource Key; (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - From Hirschman, Jack, 1967-1972, undated; Archival Resource Key; (10 letters; see also OV 7) (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Oversized From Hirschman, Jack, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - From Johnson, Ray, 1965-1968, undated; Archival Resource Key; (9 letters) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Scope and Contents
    This folder includes two pieces of correspondence from mail artist Richard C., one of which is signed for Ray Johnson by Richard C.
  - From McClure, Michael, 1957-1971, undated; Archival Resource Key; (26 letters) (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
  - From Meltzer, David, 1970, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - From Miller, Henry, 1964; Archival Resource Key; (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - From Perkoff, Stuart, 1973, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - From Weiners, John, 1960-1969; Archival Resource Key; (11 letters) (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
- Notes from Interview, 1967; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder box 1
  This series consists of one folder of sentence fragements taken from a London interview of Berman undertaken by Sandrada.
  Notes from interview are on reel 5282.
  - Notes from London Interview by Sandrada, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Writings by Others, 1972, undated; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders box 1
  This series includes a typescripts for two manuscripts and poems by Michael McClure, David Meltzer, and John Wieners.
  Writings by others are on reel 5282.
  - Typescript: "Eats" by Unidentified Author, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Typescript for Book Love Lion Book, by Michael McClure, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Poem by Unidentified Author, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Poems by Michael McClure, 1972, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Poems by David Meltzer, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Poem by John Wieners, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Artwork, 1956-1976; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1, OV 7
  This series consists of eleven collages and nine drawings by Berman, and eight "photograms" by Robert F. Heinecken.
  Artwork is on reel 5282.
  - Artwork by Berman, 1956-1976, undated; Archival Resource Key; (see also OV 7) (Box 1, Folder 33-35)
  - Oversized Artwork by Berman, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Artwork by Others-Photograms by Robert F. Heinecken, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Semina, 1955-1967; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 26 Folders boxes 1-2
  This series consists of copies of Berman's mail art publication Semina. There are multiple copies of Nos. 1, 2, 4-8, and an envelope for No. 9. The files also contains Semina Art Gallery announcements.
  Semina files are on reel 5282.
  - Semina, Nos. 1 - 9, 1955-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37-51)
  - Semina, Nos. 1 - 9 cont., 1955-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
  - Semina Art Gallery Announcements, [1965-1967]; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
- S. M. S., 1968; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder box 2
  This series consists of a copy of No. 1 of the mail art publication S. M. S.
  S.M.S. file is on reel 5282.
  - S. M. S., No. 1, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Printed Material, 1907-1976; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 2.7 Linear feet boxes 2-5
  This series consists of clippings, exhibition announcements, catalogs, brochures, booklets, scripts written by Berman's colleagues, seventy-four books, and miscellaneous printed material. Exhibition announcements and catalogs for others includes a catalog authographed by Jasper Johns.
  The series is arranged as two subseries.
  7.1: General Printed Material, 1908-1976
  7.2: Books, 1907-1974, undated
  Printed materials are on reels 5282-5284.
  - General Printed Material, 1908-1976, 7.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Clippings, 1962-1976, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12-24)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Berman, 1968-1975, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25-29)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1964-1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
    - Brochures, 1964-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Booklets, "Kolner Puppen-Theater," Vols. 2, 4, by Fritz Honig, 1908-1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Booklets, "Work of the Chariot,", 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Booklets, ["Moulin a Papier Richard de Bas in Ambert, France,", 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Scripts, The Beard, by Michael McClure, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Scripts, The Yin and the Yang, by Don Sherman, Dennis Hopper, and Peter Fonda, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Books, 1907-1974, undated; 7.2; Archival Resource Key
    The books in this subseries include works on various religions, theories, and philosophies fundamental to the beat movement. There are first edition publications by many of the movement's leaders.
    The books are arranged chronolgically.
    - Phanopoeia Pavane: Dance - Play in Verse by unidentified author, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Another Academy by Charles Bukowski, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Kabbalah by Rabbi Levi L. Krakowsky, undated, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Osma of Oz by L. Frank Baum, 1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - The Book of formation or Sepher Yetzirah by Knut Stenring, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - The Story of Modern Science by Henry Smith Williams, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Rota ou & La Roue Celeste by Enel, 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - The Chinese Written Character as a Medium for Poetry by Ernest Fenollosa, edited by Ezra Pound, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - The Journal of Albion Moonlight by Kenneth Patchen, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Pictures of Life and of Death by Kenneth Patchen, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Poems 1948-49 by Robert Duncan, [1949]; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Waters Reglitterized by Henry Miller, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Howl by Allen Ginsberg, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - The Pearl Tears by Nickolas Logan, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Collectanea: I E Alexander, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Images de Jean Cocteau, preface de Georges Noel, [1957?]; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - The Wisdom of the Kabbalah, foreword by Dagobert D. Runes, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Hymns to St. Geryon and Other Poems by Michael McClure, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Ragas by David Meltzer, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Letters by Robert Duncan, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Gallery of Women by Ruth Weiss, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - The First War Planes by William E. Barrett, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - A Correspondence of Americans by Jack Hirschman, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Wobbly Rock by Lew Welch, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Poems for Selected People by Idell, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Destroyed Works by Philip Lamantia, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - We All Have Something to Say to Each Other by David Meltzer, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Robert Ronnie Branaman, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Television Decollage & Morning Glory/ 2 Pieces by Volf Vostell, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Points in Time by Zack Walsh, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Ballads by Helen Adams, illustrated by Jess, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Black Pilgrimage by Cameron, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Ghost Tantras by Michael McClure, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - The Esoteric Tarot by Simon Kasdin, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Process by David Meltzer, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Chinoiserie by John Wieners, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - The Hotel Wentley Poems by John Wieners, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Bruce Connor/Michael McClure, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Sapphobones by Kirby Doyle, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - A Portents Semina, Portents #6, (for Wallace Berman) By Samuel Charters, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - A Dream by Steve Elvin, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Love Dragon Poem by Michael L. Fram, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - The Soap Opera by Piero Heliczer, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - William Blake by Jack Hirschman, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Zen Love Poems by Idell, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Golden Sardine by Bob Kaufman, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Lying Together; Turning the Head & Shifting the Weight; The Produce District, & Other Places; Moving -- A Spring Poem by Ron Loewinsohn, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Business Cards by Billy Al Bengston and Ed Ruscha, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - The Finger by Bobbie Creeley, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Hail Thee Who Play by Michael McClure, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Round the Poem Box; Rustic & Domestic Home Movies for Stan & Jane Brakhage by David Meltzer, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Black Alephs by Jack Hirschman, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Shekinah by Jack Hirschman, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Hymns to St. Geryon and Other Poems/Dark Brown by Michael McClure, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Gallowsongs: Galgenlieder by Christian Morgenstern Versions by Jess, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - General Principles of the Kabbalah by Rabbi Moses C. Luzzatto, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Greenspeech by David Meltzer, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Luna by David Meltzer, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Altars by Clayton Eshhleman, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Scintilla by Jack Hirschman, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Knots by David Meltzer, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - An Excerpt from "The Disconcerting Games of Vadim the Mechanic" by Ben Talbert, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Kabbala Surrealism: An Essay and The R of the Ari's Raziel by Jack Hirschman, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - The Mammals by Michael McClure, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Spectral Measures on the Unit Disc by Bartholomew, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Hero/Lil by David Meltzer, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Kabbalah by Charles Ponce, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Alphabet by Stuart Z. Perkoff, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Cantillations and DJackson by Jack Hirschman, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Igitur by Stephane Mallarme, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Rare Angel by Michael McClure, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - September Blackberries by Michael McClure, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Miscelaneous Printed Material, 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1956-1976; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders box 5, OV 7
  This series contains photgraphs of Berman, his wife, his colleagues, the Poets' Parade, and his work Wall Painting. The five photographs of Berman show him with Artie Richer, B. Alexander, David Meltzer at Fergus Gallery, his son Tosh, and William Hillman. Photographs of colleagues include: Cameron, 1962; Richard Constantino, 1958; S. Berman and Samson de Brier, 1956; Samson de Brier, 1957; Bill Eisenlord, undated; George Herms, 1960; Louise Herms, 1958; Pat Jordan, 1960; Philip Lamantia, 1958 and 1959; Michael McClure (16 undated photographs); Artie Richer with Berman, 1958; John Wieners, 1959 and 1964.
  Photographs are on reel 5284.
  - Photographs of Berman, 1957-1976; Archival Resource Key; (5 photographs; see also OV 7) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Photographs of Berman, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Photographs of Colleagues, 1956-1964; Archival Resource Key; (see also OV 7) (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
  - Oversized Photographs of Colleagues, Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Photographs of the Poets' Parade, 1958; Archival Resource Key; (3 photographs) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Artwork "Wall Painting" by Berman, 1974; Archival Resource Key; (2 photographs) (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Sound Recordings, 1962-1965; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders box 6
  This series contains twelve reel-to-reel tapes of poetry readings by Micahel McClure, David Meltzer, and Kenneth Patchen.
  - Michael McClure and Unidentified Poet Performing with Sound Effects, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Poetry Readings by David Meltzer and Kenneth Patchen, 1962; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Michael McClure Poetry Reading at the Lion House, San Francisco; recorded by Bruce Kansas Connor, 1965; Archival Resource Key; 10 Sound tape reels multiple copies of limited edition sound publication; (9 identical copies) (Box 6, Folder 3-6)